Did you hear about Ayano?
聞いた 綾野さんのこと
She was trying to escape, wasn't she?
あれってさ 逃げようとしたんだよね
I think so.
だと思う
You think she died because
she tried to get away?
逃げようとしたから死んだってこと
I don't know...
分かんない
Ogura's brother died that same day, didn't he?
同じ日に
小椋のお兄さんも 何でしょ
Hadn't he shut himself up at home?
引きこもってたんだよね
みたい
あのさ 合宿なんだけどね
You know, I heard something
about the class trip.
Apparently, it does have significance.
意味が あるらしいよ
Significance?
意味って
You mean, asking the gods for help?
何それ
神頼み
I heard the class was saved once
by doing that.
それで助かった年があるんだって
Yoru o oou mabuta hirake
夜ヲ覆ウ目蓋開ケ
凶キ影ヲ恐レルナカレ
Waruki kage o osoreru nakare
Honoguraki hitsugi kara
仄くらき柩から
Umiotosareta ningyou no you ni
産み堕とされた人形のように
Karada wa akaku kogoe
躰は赤く凍え
Kokoro wa yami ni ayasare sodatsu
心は闇にあやされ育つ
Kimi ni boku ga mieru kai
君に僕が見えるかい
Tsunagu te no tsumetasa ni
つなぐ手の冷たさに
Senketsu no tsume tateru
鮮血の爪立てる
Mayu yosete goran yo
眉寄せてごらんよ
壊し合おう先に続く 謎に満ちる結末を
Kowashiaou saki ni tsuzuku
Nazo ni michiru ketsumatsu o
Hane mo ashi mo mogareta mama
羽も脚ももがれたまま
Kokuu no naka kuchihateru yori
虚空のなか朽ち果てるより
Mou hitori boku ga ite
もうひとり僕がいて
Dareka o itai hodo aishite irun da
誰かを痛いほど愛しているんだ
Saa docchi ga maboroshi darou ne
さぁどっちが幻だろうね
Stupid...
バカ
Stupid brother!
お兄のバ バカ
バカ
You idiot!
イテッ
Ouch!
すみません 大丈夫ですか
I'm sorry! Are you all right?
You okay?
大丈夫
Nice to meet you.
よろしく
I'm Kouichi Sakakibara.
榊原恒一です
Sakitani
Memorial
Hall
テープは
Got the tape?
Yep.
持ってきたよ
Listen to it?
聞いた
Not yet.
まだ
I'm afraid to listen to it alone.
一人で聞くのは怖くて
Let's take a picture to
commemorate this occasion.
写真撮ろうよ
記念写真
It's our last summer break
in junior high after all.
中学最後の夏休みなんだから
Okay?
Sakitani
Memorial
Hall
Everyone line up over there.
皆 そこに並んで
Perfect.
そう そう
Let's get the teachers in the shot too.
先生も入ってくださいね
Okay, almost ready.
はい 撮りますよ
Sakakibara and Misaki,
squeeze a little closer together.
榊原くんと見崎さん もうちょっと寄って
You should get to be in one too.
望月 お前も入れ
I'll take it for you.
撮ってやるよ
Here goes!
撮るぞ
Mochizuki, you and Ms. Mikami
are too far apart!
おい 望月 先生と遠いぞ
Same goes for Sakaki and Misaki!
サカキと見崎もだ
Kazami, you're fine there.
風見はそのままでいい
All right, say "cheese!"
はい チーズ
Tomorrow, we'll visit the shrine
to pray for our safety.
明日は皆で神社にお参りをして
クラスの無事をお願いしましょう
Right!
はい
This is a nice lodge.
立派な合宿所ですね
A local business donated
its recreation center.
地元の企業が使っていた保養所を寄付してくれたんだよ
It seems a bit extravagant for
a school group, if you ask me.
正直なところ 学校では持て余しているようだがね
Welcome!
ようこそ いらっしゃいました
We've kept all the rooms open for you.
お部屋のほうは全部空けてありますからね
Thank you for having us for
the next three days.
これから三日間 よろしくお願いします
あい こちらこそ
We're happy to, thanks for coming.
If there's anything you need,
don't hesitate to ask.
何かありましたら 何なりと言ってくださいね
Okay...
じゃあ
I'm playing it.
再生するぞ
Now, this is the important part.
肝心なのはこの後だ
Right after we finally reached
the bottom of the mountain,
やっとの思いで下山した直後
that's when it happened.
それがあったんだ
And by it, I mean...
それっていうのは
つまり
I...
俺が
場所は合宿所の外の森の中だった
It happened in the forest,
outside the lodge.
I got into an argument with a guy named [*].
そこで俺…ていうやつと言い争いになって
We ended up trading blows.
それから 掴み合いの喧嘩になったんだ
And then... And then...
それで それで
The next thing I knew, he wasn't moving.
気がついた時には あいつ動かなくなってたんだ
He was lying under a huge tree.
森の中のデッカイ木の下に倒れてて
When I looked closer,
近寄って見たら
木の枝が突き刺さってて
I saw he'd been impaled on a branch.
[*] was dead.
…が 死んでた
Terrified, I ran back to my room at the lodge.
俺怖くなって
合宿所の部屋に逃げ帰ったんだ
It had been decided that
we'd be staying an extra night.
その日はもう一泊合宿所で休んでいくことになって
The police came to see us about
the lightning and the fall.
落雷や滑落のことで 警察もやって来て
あれこれ質問されたけど
They asked me a lot of questions,
but I couldn't tell them anything about [*].
…のことは 何も言えなかった
I hardly slept at all that night.
結局 ほとんど眠れなかった
I was sure someone would find [*]'s
body and everyone would freak.
誰かが…の死体を見つけて
大騒ぎになるんじゃないかって
But in the morning, there were
no signs of that happening,
なのに
朝になっても全然そんな気配がなかったんだ
so I went back into the forest to find it myself.
それで俺 確かめに行ったんだよ
…の死体がある森の中へ
そしたら
But...
なかったんだよ
It wasn't there!
死体が消えてたんだ
It had vanished without a trace.
跡形もなく
I was so bewildered...
俺はすっかり混乱しちまって
I asked the others what had happened to [*].
皆に聞いてみたんだ
「…はどうしたのかな」って
But they all just looked at me like I was crazy.
すると 皆が皆変な顔すんだよ
"Who's that?"
「誰だよ それ」って
"I don't know anyone with that name."
「そんなやつ知らない」って
They even said there were nineteen
students on the trip, not twenty.
しかも 合宿に参加した生徒は
20人じゃなくて19人だって言うんだ
That's when it dawned on me...
そこでやっと俺 思い当たったのさ
The guy I'd killed, [*],
俺が殺したあいつ
must have been the extra student all along.
…がきっと今年クラスに紛れ込んでた「もう一人」だったんだって
I know without a doubt that I killed [*].
俺はあの時 確かに…を殺した
Nothing will change that fact.
この事実に変わりはない
That's why I decided to come clean here.
だから ここで告白しておこうと決めた
This is my confession.
これが俺の罪の告白だ
It's been two weeks since the trip,
合宿から二週間
and only I, the sole person deeply involved
in his death, still remember [*].
…の死と深く関わった俺だけは
まだあいつのことを覚えてる
But I get the feeling it's only a matter of time.
でも それも時間の問題じゃないかって気がする
That's why, while my memory is still clear,
だから 記憶がまだ確かなうちに
I want to tell you the truth,
この事実を
and how to stop the calamity.
どうやったら災厄を止められるかを伝えようと思って
Are you listening?
いいか
Send them back to death, where they belong.
「死者」を死に帰せ
Send the dead back to death.
「死者」を死に帰すんだ
That's how to stop the calamity
once it's begun.
それが 始まってしまった災厄を止める方法だ
We couldn't hear his name.
名前 分からなかったね
Does that mean this has been altered?
これも 改竄されてるってこと
Probably.
たぶん
Then, it must be real.
なら これ本物だね
There'd be no reason to alter a fake.
いたずらなら 改竄されないはずよね
Well, we don't need the name.
まあ 名前はいいや
What matters is how to stop the calamity.
それより 止める方法だろ
They say there's no way to tell
the dead from the living.
「死者」って 僕らと見分けがつかないって
And they don't know they're dead.
本人も気づいてないらしいし
Is there any way to tell at all?
見分ける方法なんてあるのかよ
There doesn't seem to be.
ないって聞いたよ
Mr. Matsunaga's case was pure coincidence.
松永さんの場合は偶然だったみたいだし
You don't suppose the extra student is here,
at this lodge, do you?
あのさ
この合宿に来てるかな「もう一人」
Say we do figure out who it is...
仮に 誰が「もう一人」なのか分かったとしてさ
Then what?
それで どうするの
Are we supposed to...
そいつを殺す
kill them?
Well...
そりゃあ
Could you kill a classmate?
同級生を 殺せる
You know,
な 俺さ
I've been thinking about who
the extra could be.
「もう一人」が誰なのか ずっと考えてんだけどさ
Do you have someone in mind?
見当がついたとか
Well, I...
それは
I just think there must be
some way to tell who it is.
「もう一人」を見分ける方法さ なんかあるんじゃないかって
Keep inhaler in bag
when not in use.
Maybe there is, and we just don't know it yet.
まだ分かってないだけなのかもしれないしね
Exactly.
だろう
May I have a moment, Ms. Mikami?
ちょっといいでしょうか 先生
この際ですから 言っておきたいことがあるんです
Since we're all together,
there's something I'd like to say.
Is that all right?
よろしいでしょうか
Um, sure.
そうね
Go ahead, Akazawa.
どうぞ 赤沢さん
Since May, we have experienced
nothing but misfortune.
5月から度重なる不幸があって
Just last month, even
Mr. Kubodera became a victim.
先月は久保寺先生まで あんなことになってしまって
To begin,
まず対策係として
I'd like to apologize for my great ineptitude
as the head of countermeasures.
いくつかの不手際があったことをお詫びします
それと
In addition,
though it remains unclear whether this trip
will lead us toward a resolution,
この合宿で事態が収拾に向かうのかまだ分からないところですが
少なくとも これまでの災いの数々については
I sincerely believe that you, Misaki,
見崎さん あなたに責任の一端があると思うの
bear some degree of responsibility
for the disasters we've faced.
Why?
どうして
見崎さんが決まりどおりに
If Misaki had properly upheld her role
as the nonexistent student,
「いないもの」の役割をまっとうしていれば
I believe no one would have died.
誰も死なずに済んだはず
Hold on!
ちょっと待った
What happened was unavoidable.
そいつは不可抗力っつうかさ
She couldn't help how it all went down.
仕方ない成り行きだったんじゃねえ
Really, now?
She couldn't help how it all went down.
そうかしら
If she had been completely thorough
in avoiding contact with Sakakibara,
見崎さんがあくまで榊原くんの接触を拒む
という態度を徹底していれば
the countermeasure would have succeeded.
対策は成功したはず
But...
それは
そもそもの失敗の責任はまず
I believe the primary person responsible
But...
for its failure is Misaki.
見崎さんにあると思うの
Wouldn't you agree?
そうでしょう
What do you expect her to do about it now?
だから今 どうしろって
Apologize.
謝罪を
We have yet to hear one word
of apology from her.
私達 一言も見崎さんから謝罪の言葉を聞いてない
なのに 見崎さん
Yet, Misaki, the moment you were
allowed to exist again,
あなた「いないもの」じゃなくなった途端
you carried on as if nothing happened.
何事もなかったみたいに
There's no point.
不毛ね
して 意味がある
Would apologizing serve any purpose?
If it will, I'll do it.
あるのならするけど
Misaki, you have nothing to apologize for.
見崎 しなくていいよ 謝罪なんて
ごめんなさい
I'm sorry.
It's my fault.
私のせいで
違う
It's not!
Stop it!
止めてよ
This is pointless!
意味ねえよ
What's important is figuring out
who the extra...
それよかさ
肝心なのは「もう一人」が誰なのかを
Hey, Wakui, are you okay?
おい 和久井 大丈夫か
Are you in pain?
苦しいのか
Hey!
おい
Is this boy asthmatic?
この生徒には喘息の持病が
Yes, he always has this.
そうです いつもこの薬を
吸入薬
An inhaler?
Shouldn't he use this?
使ってもだめなのか
空なのか
It's empty?
Do you have a spare?
用意は
Call an ambulance!
救急車
三神先生 すぐに救急車を
Ms. Mikami, call an ambulance now!
Um...
その
Our phones haven't been
working since yesterday.
昨日から電話の調子が悪くて 繋がらないんです
We can't make calls.
We've arranged for repairs...
ですから修理に
だめだ 圏外だ
It's out of range.
We've arranged for repairs...
Does anyone have service?
繋がるものはいないか
Call 119! Get an ambulance here!
119番にかけて 救急車を
It says there's an antenna here,
but I can't connect!
アンテナ立ってんのに 繋がんねえ
Mine won't work either.
僕のもダメです
There's no service.
繋がりません
I'll drive him to the hospital.
私の車で病院に運ぼう
Are you all right?
大丈夫ですか
I'm not the one you should be worried about.
私の心配はいいから ね
Maybe we shouldn't go up
the mountain tomorrow.
明日山に登るのは 中止にしたほうが
Maybe not.
そう ね
Sakakibara...
榊原くん
Yeah?
なに
Thanks for earlier.
さっきはありがとう
Huh?
さっき 食堂で色々言われた時
You stood up for me in the dining room.
Oh, that, it was nothing.
いや 別にそんな
And it wasn't just me.
僕だけじゃないよ
There was Mochizuki and Teshigawara too.
望月だって 勅使河原だって
Thank you.
There was Mochizuki and Teshigawara too.
ありがとう
Will you come see me later?
後で来てくれる
I have my own room, and...
私の部屋 同室の子はいないから
それに
I want to see the photo.
写真も見せて欲しいし
Where was it?
どこにあったの
In a detached room at our house.
離れにあったみたい
My grandma found it.
お婆ちゃんが見つけてくれて
I don't know why it was in there though.
何で離れにあったのか分かんないけど
Really?
そうなの
My aunt, Reiko, uses that room.
離れは怜子さん おばさんが使ってるんだけどね
With everyone in Grade 9, Class 3
March 16, 1973
Can you tell which one Misaki Yomiyama is?
分かる 榊原くん
どの子が夜見山ミサキくんなのか
Well, I can see that one person looks strange.
それは なにかほら 見るからに変な感じだし
変に見える
Strange?
In what way?
どんなふうに
Like...
どんなって
He's kind of blurry,
compared to the others in the photo.
ほかの部分に比べて 何だかそこだけぼやけてると言うか
Distorted, somehow.
歪んでると言うか
That's right.
そう
What about the color?
色は
Do you see any strange colors?
おかしな色に見えたりしない
No, not really.
いや それは別に
Thank you.
ありがとう
Are these other photos your mom's too?
ほかの写真もお母さんの
Yeah.
They really did look alike.
やっぱり似てたんだね
Who?
やっぱり
Your mother and your aunt.
お母さんと その おばさんがね
You think so?
そう見える
Their faces looked the same as kids.
子供の頃の顔がそっくり
Does Reiko do painting at home?
怜子さん 家で絵描くんだ
Yeah.
She considers that her real job.
本人曰く そっちが本職のつもりなんだってさ
I see.
そうなんだ
You were drawing something too,
weren't you?
見崎も絵描いてたよね
An angel?
天使の絵
Who was the model for that?
あれって 誰がモデルなの
It was...
それは
Your cousin Misaki?
いとこの未咲ちゃん
Maybe.
そうかもしれない
When we first met, at the hospital,
あのさ 最初に病院で会った時
その 死んだ未咲ちゃんに人形を届けに行ったの
were you taking that doll to your cousin,
after she passed away?
Do you find that strange?
変だなって思った
まあ
Uh...
It's sort of complicated.
ちょっと複雑な事情がね
I don't usually like talking about it.
あまり人には話したくないことなんだけど
Could you tell me?
聞いてもいい
Okay.
My mother Kirika's real name is Yukiyo,
私のお母さん 霧果の本名はユキヨ
and Misaki's mother's name is Mitsuyo.
未咲のお母さんはミツヨっていう名前で
They're twins, almost identical.
二人は双子で
とてもよく似てるの
When they grew up, they both got married,
でね 大人になってお互い結婚して
and Mitsuyo became a mother.
ミツヨの方に子供が生まれたの
To your cousin Misaki?
その子供が未咲さん
And one other.
それと もう一人
Huh?
She had twins.
生まれたのは双子だったの
Twins?
双子
One year later, Yukiyo became pregnant too,
その一年後 ユキヨの方も妊娠したの
but her baby never came into this world.
でも ユキヨの赤ちゃんは生まれてこられなくて
You mentioned that.
言ってたね
Yukiyo was so grief-stricken,
she nearly had a breakdown.
ユキヨはとても苦しいんだの
気が狂ってしまいそうなほどに
To make matters worse,
the Fujioka household,
双子を授かった藤岡家の方は
into which the twins were born,
was in financial trouble.
経済的な不安があったの
The Misaki household, on the other hand,
対する見崎家の方は ユキヨの心を何とか救う必要があった
needed something to soothe Yukiyo's heart.
It was a matter of supply and demand.
ここでね 需要と供給があったわけ
You mean...
それって
I was given to her.
You mean...
出されたのが 私
I think they gave me to her,
instead of Misaki,
どうして未咲じゃなくて私が出されたかって言うのは
because of my name.
たぶん 名前のせい
Your name?
名前
もし未咲の方が見崎家の養女になったら
If the Misakis took in
a daughter named Misaki,
見崎未咲でしょ
her name would be Misaki Misaki.
I've been raised as Yukiyo's...
物心つかないうちから
私はユキヨ
霧果の一人娘として育てられたの
as Kirika's only daughter,
for as long as I can remember.
I think I was in 5th grade
when I discovered the truth.
真実を知ったのは小学校五年生の時だったかな
My grandmother accidentally let it slip.
お婆ちゃんがうっかり口を滑らせて
あの時の母さんの慌てっぷりったらなかった
I've never seen my mother so flustered.
She was probably planning
to keep it a secret my whole life.
たぶん 一生隠しておきたかったんだろうな
What happened once you knew the truth?
本当のことを知って それで
I wanted to meet Mitsuyo Fujioka,
my other mother,
会いたいって思ったよ
藤岡のお母さんに
and I told Kirika that.
それで 私 霧果にそう言ったの
At first, she looked incredibly sad.
そうしたら あの人 凄く悲しそうな顔をして
But then she was furious.
凄く怒り出して
She didn't want you to meet
your birth mother?
産みのお母さんに会わせたくなくて
みたいね
I guess not.
She doesn't interfere in my life much,
基本 放任なんだけど
except, as I've mentioned, for certain things.
あることを除いてはって
Right, I remember.
I think she feels anxious.
不安になるんだと思うの
That's probably why she makes me
carry a cell phone.
私に携帯を持たせるのも たぶん その不安の表れね
But while all that was going on,
でも
そんな中でも 未咲とはこっそり会ってたの
I was secretly meeting with Misaki.
By then, she also knew that we were twins.
その頃には未咲の方も 私たちが双子だって分かってたし
We felt that we were connected,
whether we wanted to be or not.
あの子と私とは 否応なしに繋がってる気がしてた
She often snuck over to my house.
未咲もこっそり私の家に遊びに来ててね
She said she liked my house because
it was full of pretty dolls.
「鳴の家には すてきな人形がいっぱいあっていいね」って
When I asked her what she wanted
for her birthday in April,
それでね
四月の誕生日に何が欲しいって聞いたら
she said, "I want that doll."
未咲が「あの人形がいい」って
なのに 三年生に上がってすぐ 急に
But soon after starting 9th grade,
she suddenly...
それが あの時の
That's what you were doing?
I had made a promise to her.
約束だったから
So you were sisters, not cousins.
いとこじゃなくて 姉妹
そう
Yes.
That's why you told me,
だからあの時
"It may have already begun."
「もう始まってるかもしれない」って
よく覚えてるのね
So you remember that.
Yes.
そう
Why didn't you tell me that day?
どうしてあの時 教えてくれなかったの
I...
私
I just...
私はね
I didn't want to believe it.
信じたくなかった
そんな わけの分からない呪いみたいなもので
I didn't want to believe Misaki had died
because of some crazy curse.
未咲が死んでしまったなんて
That's why...
だから いとことしか言えなかった
I could only call her my cousin.
I didn't want to say it.
言いたくなかった
The Misaki who died in April
was the first victim.
四月に亡くなった未咲ちゃんが
最初の犠牲者
だったとしたら
If that's true, then...
つまり
Everyone else seems to think the
calamity began in May, but...
皆は 今年の「災厄」は五月から始まったんだって
思ってるみたいだけど
僕が夜見北に来る前から
The extra student was already in the class
before I came to Yomi North.
クラスには「もう一人」がいた
Is that why you're so certain
that I'm not dead?
だからなの
きっぱり「違う」って言ったよね 僕が「死者」じゃないって
Yes.
四月には 僕がクラスにいなかったから
Because I wasn't in the class back in April?
それもあるけど
There's that, but it's not the main reason.
一番の理由じゃない
What's your main reason?
一番の理由って
It's...
それは
This eye.
この目が
This doll's eye tells me you're not.
この「人形の目」が「違う」って教えてくれるから
Your left eye?
左目
I think I told you
言ったよね
that it lets me see things
that should remain unseen.
見えなくていいものが見えるって
Yeah.
うん 何が見えるの
What can it see?
The...
それは
color of death.
「死の色」
The color of things close to death.
「死」のそばにある物の色
Color?
色
What color is that?
どんな色なの
A color I've never seen with my right eye.
右の目では見たことがない色
It doesn't belong with colors
like red and blue.
赤とか 青とか
どれも当て嵌まらない
そんな色
It's unique.
And you can only see that color
in people who are dead?
死んだ人だけなの その色が見えるのは
死んでる場合は はっきり
It's clearest in dead people,
and faint in those with
serious illnesses or injuries.
重病とか重傷の人は うっすら
それって 「死」に近い人が分かるってこと
You mean, you can tell when
people are about to die?
You can't understand how I can
see these things, right?
どうしてそんなものが見えるのか
不思議に思うでしょう
Well...
それは
I've had to accept it.
でも 受け入れるしかなかった
I've never even talked to Misaki about this.
こんな話 未咲にだってちゃんと話したことなかった
At some point, I decided to keep this eye
covered for the rest of my life.
それで
ある時期から
この目はずっと隠したままでいようって決めたの
That's why I wanted to see that photo
from twenty-six years ago.
だからね 二十六年前のあの写真を 一度ちゃんと見てみたかったの
You could see the color of death
in Misaki Yomiyama?
この写真 夜見山ミサキに 「死」の色は見えた
Yes.
見えたよ
It's the first time I've ever seen that color
so clearly in a photo.
写真であんなにはっきり色を感じたのは 初めてだった
I don't see the color of death in you.
榊原くんには 「死」の色は感じられない
That's how I know it's not you.
だからね あなたは違うの
You're not the extra.
「もう一人」じゃない
And you know it's not you
for the same reason?
同じ理由で
君自身も違うと分かるわけか
それじゃ もう分かってるの
Does that mean you already know
who the extra person is?
誰が「もう一人」なのか
I try to keep my eyepatch on at school.
学校では 私 ずっと眼帯は外さないようにしてたから
But you wrote "Who is dead?" on your desk.
「死者は誰」って
あんな落書きしてたのに
It wasn't as if my finding out
would change anything.
分かっても どうなるものでもないし
I did wonder though.
気にはなったけど
So...
だから ね
What about now?
今は
Is the dead person here on this trip?
この合宿に そいつは来てるの
The extra person...
「もう一人」は 来てる
is here.
Who is it?
誰
It's...
それは
サカキ
Sakaki!
俺
I think I might have done something bad!
やっちまったかも
Iro aseteku firumu no you ni
色褪せてく フィルムのように
Tashika na ima mo izure kasunde
確かな今も いずれ霞んで
Nan de mo naku waraiatta
何でもなく 笑いあった
Setsuna no jikan to hikari
刹那の時間と光
繋がってゆく 記憶の底に
Tsunagatte yuku kioku no soko ni
Dareka ga mitsukeru tame aru to
誰かが見つけるためあると信じてる 今でも
Shinjiteru ima de mo
"Makeup"